Guide to the AIDS Service Providers Association, 1987-1993
UCSF Library CKM
AIDS Service Providers Association,
1987-1993
MSS 93-36
AIDS Service Providers Association
Volume: 2 cubic feet
University of California, San Francisco. Library. Archives and Special Collections San Francisco, California 94143-0840
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Scope and Content
Agency records suffer from the effects of several changes of administrators and office managers; subsequent inconsistencies are evident in the creation, arrangement and preservation of files. While some series are incomplete, they do possess research value. The files have been arranged by function, then by chronology.
Some ASPA records document significant trends in the service provider community, among these are files that record the development of public policy, initiation of workshops to confront problems common among service providing agencies, and joint lobbying efforts. The series of member surveys is also notable, particularly the swiftly conducted investigation of damage to AIDS organizations from the 1989 Loma Prieta Earthquake.
Among the correspondence is a letter dated Oct 14, 1992 from a Susan Penner which accompanies her report on a survey she conducted of 80 service agencies during 1991/92. Her results, including CEO's attitudes towards the consolidation of certain administrative functions among agencies, will be of interest to researchers studying administrative costs of providing AIDS-related services. In general, the correspondence files provide some information about the cultural and political interactions among administrators of AIDS agencies. Other notable contents include the three editions of the HIV Referral Directory (1990, 1992, 1993) as well as a survey of volunteers and a survey of 102 AIDS agencies and their positions on issues of public policy. A final file of interest is the remarkable "Housing Rights" document compiled by PWA Gary Harmon after he was denied federally subsidized housing in Oakland.
The records include planning and founding documents, minutes, correspondence, surveys, reports, workshop and training files, and publications.
Organizational History
The AIDS Service Providers Association (ASPA) was a major conduit of information among service providers during its brief, five year existence. Its mission states that ASPA "promotes collaboration and coordination among AIDS service and community-based organizations in the eleven-county San Francisco and Monterey Bay Areas, and promotes advocacy on behalf of the AIDS service community".
It was started (initially as BAYCARE) in 1988 by Bob Munk, then deputy director of the Names Project, to network and coordinate fundraising among AIDS organization in San Francisco. Nancy DeStefanis followed Munk as Executive Director from 1990-1992. Tim Wolfred stepped in as acting Director in March of 1992, remaining in that position until a declining membership and lack of funds forced its termination in June of 1993. A twelve member, elected Board of Directors served to formulate policy, appoint and supervise staff, and oversee operations. In addition to the Executive Director, staff generally consisted of one person, who acted as office manager and membership coordinator. ASPA's major contributions were publication of its newsletter and directory, coordination of public policy and advocacy, and the provision of technical assistance to AIDS agencies.
Container List
- Pre-ASPA records
  - BAYCARE: creation and development (1987-1988) (Carton Ctn. 1)
  - Needs survey (1987)
  - News from BAYCARE, 1988
- Board of Directors
  - First ASPA meeting (Jan 1989) (Carton Ctn. 1)
  - ASPA incorporation papers, bylaws, and non-profit papers
  - Bylaws change, 1991
  - Mission statement
  - Board recruitment and operations
  - Board elections, 7/89
  - Board elections, 7/90
  - Minutes (12/88-12/89)
  - Minutes (1990)
  - Minutes (1/91-6/91)
  - Minutes (7/91-12/91)
  - Minutes (1992)
  - Minutes (1993)
  - Retreat (10/89)
  - Retreat (11/91)
  - Personnel policies: 1991, 1992
- Executive Director
  - Correspondence (1987-1988) (Carton Ctn. 1)
  - Correspondence (1989)
  - Correspondence (1990)
  - Correspondence (1991)
  - Correspondence (1992-1993)
- Member Services
  - Correspondence - member services (1992-1993) (Carton Ctn. 1)
  - Membership reports
  - Membership applications, information, solicitation letters
  - Regional meeting: San Mateo (5/7/91), (2/7/92)
  - Regional meeting: Monterey/Santa Cruz (8/15/91)
  - Regional meeting: San Francisco (8/20/91)
  - Regional meeting: Alameda/Contra Costa (10/18/91)
  - Regional meeting: Marin/Sonoma/Napa (10/23/91)
  - Regional meeting: Santa Clara (5/28/92)
- Publications
  - Press releases (Carton Ctn. 1)
  - ASPA Newsletter (1/89-6/93)
  - Newsletter: photos
  - Newsletter: contact Sheets
  - Newsletter development
  - Directory of AIDS Service Providers 1990
  - HIV Referral Directory (2nd Ed) 1992
  - HIV Referral Directory (2nd Ed) 1992 Directory Update 1/93
  - Directory development (1990-1991)
- Development
  - Development team (Carton Ctn. 2)
  - Fundraising: Under One Roof, 1991
  - Fundraising: River Romp V, 1991
  - Fundraising: AIDS Bike-A-Thon, 1992
  - Annual report, 1989
  - Developing annual report (1990-1991)
  - ASPA first anniversary event
  - Survey on volunteers: forms results (1990)
  - AIDS Volunteer Planning Group
  - Volunteer projects
- Public Policy
  - Public Policy Advisory Group (9/90-11/92) (Carton Ctn. 2)
  - NCG grant to develop HIV Public Policy Network (11/90-5/91)
  - Public policy workshop (4/19/91)
  - Public policy survey: completed Forms
  - Public policy survey: completed Forms
  - Public policy survey: results (1990)
  - Public policy: needle exchange (10/91-1/92)
  - Public policy: lobby state legislators (10/91-1992)
- Trainings and Workshops
  - Managing in the '90s (3/90) [flyer only] (Carton Ctn. 2)
  - Collaborative grants (6/92)
  - Media and AIDS service organizations (9/92)
  - Negotiating government contracts (10/92)
  - Technical assistance: resources (1990)
  - Responsible nonprofit mgmt ethical fundraising, (1991)
  - Empowering AIDS educators and caregivers (1991, 1992)
  - Management assistance for nonprofits (1992)
  - HIV and Americans with Disabilities Act (3/93)
- Surveys
  - Earthquake survey, 1989 (1 of 2) (Carton Ctn. 2)
  - Earthquake survey, 1989 (2 of 2)
  - Earthquake relief
  - Needs assessment (1992-1993)
  - Need for fundraising calendar - responses
- Multi-Member and Ad Hoc Organizations
  - AIDS/ARC Housing Committee (8/89-7/90; 10/91-12/91) (Carton Ctn. 2)
  - Housing Rights: [Gary Harmon forces the issue]
  - Community partnership/SF model meetings (1989)
  - HIV Community-Based Plan: funding grant
  - HIV Community-Based Plan: minutes, corresp, reports (1989-90)
  - AIDS Business Coalition (9/90-4/91)
  - HIV Support Group Coalition (7/92)
  - HIV treatment awareness week (6/89)
  - Life Lobby (10/87; 8/89; 3/90-6/90)
  - Life Lobby (12/90-1/92)
  - California Association of AIDS Agencies (1/90-2/90)
  - California Association of AIDS Agencies (3/90-5/90)
  - AIDS Budget Action Group (3/91-5/91)